Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Propaganda Leaflets ALBA.253
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Propaganda Leaflets
1936-1939
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA.253
0.69 Linear Feet in a manuscript box and an oversized flat box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Propaganda Leaflets (1936-1939) is composed of propaganda leaflets and flyers related to the Spanish Civil War. The leaflets and flyers in this collection were created by or in support of the Republican side of the conflict.
Historical Note
The Spanish Civil War (1936-1939) was a conflict between Spanish Nationalists under General Francisco Franco's military Junta and a coalition of socialist, communist, anarchist, and separatist groups known as the Republicans. Many of the groups who joined the Republicans were a part of the political left and had supported the Popular Front government of the Second Spanish Republic (1931-1939).
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Spanish Civil War Propaganda Leaflets (1936-1939) is comprised of propaganda leaflets and flyers related to the Spanish Civil War. The materials in this collection contain both visual and written propaganda designed to garner support for the Republicans. Propaganda found in this collection contains photographs of destroyed cities and wartime casualties; printed speeches meant to rally support or expose the opposition's political agendas; and cartoons and drawings designed to stress the importance of the Republican cause or warn against collaborating with the enemy. The leaflets and posters found in this collection are affiliated with Spain's Propaganda Ministry (Ministerio de Propaganda); the Central Army (Ejército del Centro) branch of Spain's Central Region Army Group; the former Prime Minister of Spain, Juan Negrín (1937-1939); and the former President of Spain, Manuel Azaña (1936-1939).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials. The accession number associated with this collection is 2001.007.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist.
Historical Note
Spain's Ministry of Propaganda (Ministerio de Propaganda) was one of the most active institutions in the production of propaganda posters in Republican Spain. It was created by the government of the socialist Francisco Largo Caballero on November 4, 1936, just two days before the central government left Madrid for Valencia. The ministry ceased to exist on May 17, 1937, when it was integrated into the Ministry of State.
Historical Note
The Central Region Army Group (Grupo de Ejércitos de la Región Central, GERC) was a branch of the Spanish Republican Army during the last phase of the Spanish Civil War. This unit was active between 1938-1939. The Central Region Army Group was composed of four armies: the Andalusian Army (Ejército de Andalucía), the Extremaduran Army (Ejército de Extremadura), the Central Army (Ejército del Centro), and the Levantine Army (Ejército de Levante).
Biographical Note
Juan Negrín (1892-1956) served as Prime Minister of the Second Spanish Republic between 1937-1939. Negrín was a Spanish physician and a leader of the Spanish Socialist Workers' Party. He served as the President of the Council of Ministers of the Second Spanish Republic and the Spanish Republican government in exile between 1937 and 1945. He died in exile in Paris, France.
Biographical Note
Manuel Azaña (1880-1940) served as Prime Minister of the Second Spanish Republic between 1931-1933 and 1936 and later as President of the Second Spanish Republic between 1936-1939. Azaña was an organizer of the Popular Front and a prominent leader of the Republican cause during the Spanish Civil War. After the Republican defeat against Nationlist forces in 1939, Azaña resigned from office, relocated to France, and died in exile a year later.
Spanish Civil War, Spain, 1936-1939; Press and propaganda.; Leaflets (printed works); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Negrín, Juan; Spain. Ministerio de Propaganda; Azaña, Manuel, 1880-1940; Spain. Ejército del Centro
- Comite Central del Partido Comunista de España (CPE), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda -- Fuego y hierro sobre Madrid, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda -- La tradición Española y los rebeldes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda -- Niños meurtos en Madrid, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Spain Ejército del Centro Comisión de Propaganda -- Legionarios! Vostros sois Españoles, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- P.S.O., U.G.T., P.C. -- A Los Trabajadores, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ¡Falangistas!, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Spain Ejército del Centro Comisión General de Guerra -- ¡Legionarrios! Sois la carne de cañón, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Spain Ejército del Centro Comisión General de Guerra -- ¡Legionarrios! ¡Regulares! El Gobierno legitimo de España, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda -- El Hospital de San Carlos, de Madrid, bombardeado por la aviación de los rebeldes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- 100.000 voluntarios de España ¿Porqué no ers tú uno de ellos?, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, 40)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda, Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- ¡Soldados! Las ciudades de la retaguardia son bombardeas por los aviadores Italianos y Alemanes, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Negrín, Juan -- Traidor el que deserte de su deber, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- ¡Campesino! Porqué luchas?, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Negrín, Juan -- Cada día de resistencia (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Negrín, Juan -- Soldados: proseguid vuestra efensa heroica de la tierra hispana, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda, Madrid -- Los rebeldes multiplican sus ataques, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda, Madrid -- Los habitantes de la ciudad siquem quedándose sin casas, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda -- ¿Verdún? Antes de la rebelión…calle de Mendizábal, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Spain Ejército del Centro Comisión General de Guerra -- Itaiani! Voi siete nati per vivere e non per morire in terra straniera, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Hemos estado en el frente, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hem estat al front, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- He lluitat contra els Italianos, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- ¡Guerrilleros de la libertad!, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Negrín, Juan -- El Gobierno conserva íntegro el temple con que nació, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
- ¡Fuego de cortina contra los ataques de los Italianos protegidos por el humo!, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- ¡Firmes en la resistencia, soldados de la Patria!, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Spain Ejército del Centro -- ¡Falangistas!, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- 100.000 voluntarios de España. Mujer! ¿Cuántos conoces tu?, undated (Box 1, Folder 30, Box 2, Folder 3)
- Spain Ejército del Centro, Comisariado General de Guerra -- ¡Campesinos! Os roban la cosecha, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Campesino: Te han quitado el hijo y lo han enviado al matadero, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Spain Ejército del Centro, Comisariado General de Guerra -- A los generales, jefes y oficiales del campo enemigo, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- ¡Falangistas!, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- En tu barrio, ¿cuántos voluntarios hay? (folder empty), undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Als covards les dones ham d'escopir = los a la cara, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Arenga "d'Tregua? ¡Jamás! O vencimiento o meurte", undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Spain Ejército del Centro, Comisariado General de Guerra -- Camerati! Mentre voi lottate e morite, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- ¡Españoles que estáis sometidos a la opresión facista!, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Negrín, Juan, Comisarios de guerra -- Sois en el Ejército los intérpretes de la causa humana, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Comisarios: En los momentos más difíciles habéis sabido contribuir a salvarlos, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Jefes y oficiales: Estad atentos a vuestros soldados, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Lasciapassare pertutti I soldati Italiani, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- ESPAÑA entre sus hijos y CATALUÑA puede reclutar 100.000 voluntarios (folder empty), undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- En tu casa ¿cuãntos voluntarios hay?, undated (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- En tu calle ¿cuantos voluntarios hay?, undated (Box 1, Folder 48-49, Box 2, Folder 9)
- El Dicho…El Hecho…, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
- ¡Hermanas que sufris en la España invadida! La España repubicana celebra hoy, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- 100.000 voluntarios de España, Mujer: ¿cuántos conoces tú?, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
- España puede reclutar entre sus hijos y Cataluña, 100.000 voluntarios, undated (Box 1, Folder 53, Box 2, Folder 11)
- Negrín, Juan -- Confiamos en el pueblo catalán, undated (Box 1, Folder 54, 66)
- Italiani, fratelli nostri!, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Cuidado con lo que haces el enemigo te mira, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Negrín, Juan -- Cataluña nos ayudará con su brío de pueblo a conseguir esa reconquista, undated (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
- A los cobardes las mujeres debenescupirles en la cara, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Colorful Propaganda Leaflets, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Cuidado con lo que hablas el enemigo te oye, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
- !Soldado¡ Tu mayor enemigo no son los tanques (folder empty), undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Italian Language Propaganda, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Negrín, Juan -- Cataluña se ha dado espontáneamente la orden de resistir, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- ¡Contra los tanques! ¡Organizar las mejores emboscadas!, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
- España es nuestra. Cataluña será siempre de sus hijos…100.000 voluntarios, undated (Box 1, Folder 67, Box 2, Folder 8)
- Compañero faltan brazos para las labores de la tierra. ¿Por qué?, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Español: Te han rebajado el salario, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
- ¡Españoles! A pesar de las mentiras de vuestros generales traidores, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Españoles, catalanes: Todos los partidos y organizaciones art, fascistas, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Españoles El Ejército e la Republica es fuerte, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
- ¡Español! Si no puedes pasarte a nuestras filas, undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Español ¿Recuerdas las grandes organizaciones obreras?, undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Spain Ejército del Centro, Comisariado General de Guerra -- Español ¿Qué piensas tú? En Bilbao no entraron españoles, undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
- España lucha por su Independencia, 100.000 voluntarios, undated (Box 1, Folder 76, Box 2, Folder 7)
- Spain Ejército del Centro, Comisariado General de Guerra -- ¡CIUDADANOS! Las fuerzas armadas de la República han iniciado la ofensiva, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Negrín, Juan -- El ejércitoinvasor ha podido comprobar que no es empresa fácil, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Donde trabajas, ¿cuántos voluntarios hay?, undated (Box 1, Folder 79-80, Box 2, Folder 16)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- En tu barrio, ¿cuántos voluntarios hay?, undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Cuando yo hablo de mi nación, que es la de todos vosotros, undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
- Españoles: Miente Franco cuando habla de su triunfo en Bilbao, undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
- ¡Españoles! ¡Luchando por Franco, undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
- ¡Españoles! Los generales facciosos han traicionado a su patria y a su pueblo dos veces, undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Españoles: El pueblo español que no quiso nunca empeñarse en una guerra fratricida, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
- Negrín, Juan -- A nadie puede ocultársele ya que la conquista de España, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Spain Ejército del Centro, Comisariado General de Guerra -- A todos los españdes honrados, a todos los amantes e la Patria, undated (Box 1, Folder 88)
- A todos los españoles y antifascistas de Sevilla, undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
- Negrín, Juan -- Al ejército popular. Alocución de Presidente del Consejo y ministro de Defensa, undated (Box 1, Folder 90)
- Falange Española tradicionalista y de la Jons, undated (Box 1, Folder 91)
- Falangista: Si eres sincero estarás avergonzado, undated (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Italiano! Perché lotti? Perché soffri? Perché vuoi morire?, undated (Box 1, Folder 93)
- ¡Viva la República!, undated (Box 1, Folder 94)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Ayuda al gobierno a perseguir al espia MUCHO OJO CAMARADA, undated (Box 1, Folder 95)
- Comisión de Auxilio Femenino -- Ayuda a los huerfanos de guerra, undated (Box 1, Folder 96)
- Various Spanish Language Propaganda, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 97-99)
- ¡Miliciano!, undated (Box 1, Folder 100)
- Joan Ferran Recader de Ripoll a Barcelona l Retorn, undated (Box 1, Folder 101)
- Speech Delivered by Dr. Enrique Carlos De La Casa Minister Pleni-Potentiary in Charge of the Spanish Embassy at Madison Square Garden, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 102)
- Propaganda Flyers, undated (Box 1, Folder 103)
- Spain Ministerio de Propaganda, Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- El Gobierno de España, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Spain Presidente Azaña (1936-1939) -- S.E. el Presidente de la República, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Espanya pot reclutar entre els seus fills I CATALUNYA 100.000 voluntaris, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Espanya lluita per la seva Indepèndencia, 100.000 voluntaris, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- 100.000 voluntaris d'Espanya. Dona! ¿Quants en coneixes?, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Consejos para defenderse contra la aviación, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Plaza de Toros de Murcia, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Espanya és nostra. Catalunya serà sempre dels seus fills, 100.000 voluntaris, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- A casa teva quants voluntaris hi ha?, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Political Cartoon -- La Traca, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Dona ¡Has de sentir l'orgull de tenir a la teva família un voluntari! 100.000 voluntaris, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- A la teva barriada ¿Quants voluntaris hi ha?, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- A leu carrer ¿Quants voluntaris hi ha?, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- Allà on treballes ¿Quants voluntaris hi ha?, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Spain Subsecretaría de Propaganda -- 100.000 voluntaris d'Espanya. Per què tu no n'ets un?, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- El Gobierno del Frente Popular ante las cortes de la República, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)